Register of the Alex N. Dragnich Papers, 1859-2008
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1938-1990 (Boxes 17-22)
  - "Historians Will Find Tito a Fertile Topic," article, Peninsula Times-Tribune, n.d. Printed copy. (Folder 8)
  - "Industrialization of Yugoslavia," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 9)
  - "Iran Violating Convention," article, Stanford Daily, n.d. Printed copy. (Folder 10)
  - "King Peter I: Culmination of Serbia's Struggle for Parliamentary Government," article, East European Quarterly, Vol. IV, No. 2, n.d. Printed copy. (Folder 11)
  - "Mihailovich in Historical Perspective," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 12)
  - "The Not Too Distant Frontier," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 13)
  - "Political Conversations with Djilas," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 14)
  - "Politics For Whom?" n.d. Holograph. (Folder 15)
  - "Republic: Frontier," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 16)
  - "The Serbian Radical Party: The Years in Power, 1903-1929," n.d. Typescript with annotations. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "The Serbian Spirit As a Legacy to America," speech, n.d. Typescript. (Folder 2)
  - "Socijalist, Seljacki Vodja u Titovoj Jugoslaviji," n.d. Typescript with annotations. (Folder 3)
  - "Some Misconceptions About Communism," n.d. Handwritten draft. (Folder 4)
  - "Some Problems of Post-Tito Yugoslavia," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 5)
  - Statement to U.S. Congress, n.d. Typescript. (Folder 6)
  - "The Threat We Face," n.d. Holograph. (Folder 7)
  - "The Unfinished Agenda," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 8)
  - Untitled fragments and writings
    - Djilas, Milovan (Folder 9-10)
    - Jovanovic, Dragoljub (Folder 11)
    - Pasic, Nikola (Folder 12)
    - Yugoslavia - History-20th century (Folder 13-15)
    - Yugoslavia - History-20th century (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
  - "The War on Religion," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 4)
  - "World Challenge to Freedom," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 5)
  - "Yugoslav Government Decision-Making and Nationality Differences," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 6)
  - "Yugoslavia: Problem of Nationalities," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 7)
  - "Yugoslavia and the Struggle Against Communism," n.d. Typescript. (Folder 8)
  - "The Assumptions of Democracy in the Light of Biological and Psychological Criticisms," masters thesis, University of California, 1938. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 9)
  - "The Development of Parliamentary Government in Serbia, 1869-1889," Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, 1939. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 10-11)
  - "Jugoslav Press and Foreign Affairs," article, Slavia, January/February 1940. Printed copy. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - "Vuk Karadzic and the Internal Politics of Milos Obrenovic," article, Slavia, December 1941. Printed copy. (Folder 2)
  - "Yugoslavia's New Constitution," article, Current History, May 1946. Printed copy. (Folder 3)
  - "The Mikhailovitch Trial," article, Current History, August 1946. Printe copy. (Folder 4)
  - Conversation with Vladimir Popovic, memorandum to the ambassador, February 9, 1950. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 5)
  - Conversation with Makiedo concerning the Decree on Cultural- Educational Institutions, memorandum to the ambassador, February 23, 1950. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 6)
  - "Decree on Cultural-Educational Institutions," memorandum to the ambassador, February 27, 1950. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 7)
  - Conversation with Gustav Vlahov, memorandum to the ambassador, April 5, 1950. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 8)
  - Interviews of Vladmir Popovic
    - December 27, 1950. Holograph. (Folder 9)
    - March 17, 1951. Holograph. (Folder 10)
  - "Tito Withstands Russian Domination," article, Current History, July 1952. Printed copy. (Folder 11)
  - Letters to the New York Times, 1953-1971. Printed copies. (Folder 12)
  - "Time to Revise Our Yugoslav Policy," article, Vital Speeches of the Day, April 1, 1953. Printed copy. (Folder 13)
  - Tito's Promised Land, Rutgers University Press, 1954. Reviews. Printed copies. (Folder 14)
  - Review of The Threat of Soviet Imperialism by C. Grove Haines, 1955. Printed copy. (Folder 15)
  - Letter to the editor, Nashville Tennessean, January 1, 1957. Printed copy. (Folder 16)
  - "How Different is Tito's Communism?" article, The American Political Science Review, March 1957. Printed copy. (Folder 17)
  - "Recent Political Developments in Yugoslavia," article, Journal of Politics, Vol. 20, 1958. (Folder 18)
  - Review of The Balkans in Our Time by Robert Lee Wolff, 1958. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 19)
  - "Four Democrats Whom Tito Jailed," article, The New Leader, June 2, 1958. Printed copy. (Folder 20)
  - "International Communism in Yugoslavia - The Myth of 'Titoism'," consultation with the Committee on Un-American Activities, U.S. House of Representatives, September 15, 1958. Printed copy. (Folder 21)
  - Testimony before the Congressional Committee, November 1958. Correspondence, clippings and related material. (Folder 22)
  - "Communism in Theory and Practice," lecture at the Naval War College, September 29, 1959. Printed copy. (Folder 23)
  - "A Political and Economic Appraisal of Greece, Turkey and Yugoslavia," article, Naval War College Review, February 1961. Printed copy. (Folder 24)
  - "Conversations with Djilas," 1967. Typescript with annotations. (Folder 25)
  - "Tito's Promised Land Revisited," outline of manuscript. Typescript. (Folder 26)
  - "The Military and Political Development in 19th Century Serbia," 1968. Typescript. Drafts, notes and related correspondence included. (Folder 27)
  - "The Serbs in Quest of Freedom," speech, Polich Room dedication at the Hoover Institution, Stanford University, March 16, 1968. Typescript. (Folder 28)
  - "Students Shake Tito Regime," October 1968. Typescript (carbon copy). (Folder 29)
  - "Yugoslavia's Forgotten Man: Dragoljub Jovanovich," 1969. Handwritten draft. (Folder 30)
  - "How Serious is the Yugoslav Crisis?" article, East Europe, October 1971. Printed copy. (Folder 31)
  - "Djilas and Mihailo Markovic, Cosic," 1972. Holograph notebook. (Folder 32)
  - "Yugoslavia: Problem of Nationalities," article, Politics 73, No. 4, March 1973. Printed copy. (Folder 33)
  - "Tito's New Crackdown: Turning Back the Clock in Yugoslavia," article, The New Leader, June 23, 1973. Printed copy. (Folder 34)
  - "Turning Back the Clock in Yugoslavia," article, The New Leader, June 25, 1973. Printed copy. (Folder 35)
  - Letter to the editor, Atlantic Monthly, October 1973. Printed copy. (Folder 36)
  - Serbia, Nikola Pasic and Yugoslavia, Rutgers University Press, 1974, reviews. Printed copies. (Folder 37)
  - "Buducnost Jugoslavije i Srpskog Naroda u Njoj," speech, 1975. Typesript with annotations. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - "Leadership and Politics: Nineteenth Century Serbia," article, Journal of Politics, Vol. 37, 1975. Printed copy. (Folder 2)
  - "Yugoslavia: Titoism Without Tito," article, Current History, March 1976. Printed copy. (Folder 3)
  - "Belgrade Notes, June 1976," June 1976. Holograph notebooks. (Folder 4)
  - "Long Dream About Tito," August 1978. Holograph. (Folder 5)
  - Review of Wartime by Milovan Djilas, 1979. Printed copy. (Folder 6)
  - "Stalemate Between President and Congress Must Be Averted," article, Boston Herald American, November 13, 1979. Printed copy. (Folder 7)
  - "What Parliament System Can Tell Us," article, Forum, December 6, 1979. Printed copy. (Folder 8)
  - "Yugoslavia," paper presented at East-Central Europe Conference, Hoover Institution, Stanford University, January 5, 1980. Typescript with annotations. (Folder 9)
  - "Yugoslav's Tito: How Will He Be Remembered in History," article, Oakland Tribune, May 7, 1980. Printe copy. (Folder 10)
  - "Do We Have Unifier? Another Lincoln Needed," article, The Intelligence, August 2, 1980. Printed copy. (Folder 11)
  - "Yugoslavia After Tito," article, Vanderbilt Alumnus, Winter 1981. Printed copy. (Folder 12)
  - "Left Remains," letter to the editor, Stanford Daily, April 1, 1981. Printed copy. (Folder 13)
  - "On Western Aid to Poland," article, The Cincinnati Post, April 15, 1981. Printed copy. (Folder 14)
  - "Tito's Troubled Legacy in Yugoslavia," October 1981. Typescript. (Folder 15)
  - "Can the Yugoslavians Cure Economic Woes?" article, Deseret News, November 2, 1981. Printed copy. (Folder 16)
  - "Reaping the Whirlwind: Tito's Troubled Legacy in Yugoslavia," 1982. Typewritten draft. (Folder 17)
  - "Tito's Troubled Legacy in Yugoslavia," article, Military Science and Technology, June 1982. Printed copy. (Folder 18)
  - "Permanence of Communist Regimes," article, Chicago Tribune, June 22, 1982. Printed copy. (Folder 19)
  - "Yugoslavia: A Giant Headache for United States," article, The Spokesman Review, April 3, 1983. Printed copy. (Folder 20)
  - Remarks at Southern Conference on Slavic Studies, Atlanta, October 7, 1983. Typescript. (Folder 21)
  - "The Not-Too-Distant Frontier," series of articles appearing in Serb World U.S.A., 1989-1990. Printed copies. (Folder 22)
- Subject File, 1859-1982 (Boxes 22-33)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, notes, printed material, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Almon, David C. (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - American Historical Association, Pacific Coast Branch, 70th annual meeting, Flagstaff, AZ, August 11-13, 1977 (Folder 24)
  - American Institute for Balkan Affairs, 1955-1963 (Folder 25)
  - American-Serbian Cultural Foundation (San Francisco), 1971-76 (Folder 26)
  - Arvin, Thomas D. (Folder 27)
  - Bell, James (Folder 28)
  - Bellquist, Eric (Folder 29)
  - Bikobbo, Robert (Folder 30)
  - Columbia Basin Reclamation Project, 1946 (Folder 31)
  - Communist Party of Yugoslavia
    - Comintern, 1941-42 (Folder 32)
    - Fifth Congress, proceedings, July 1948 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
    - Nationality question (Folder 3)
  - Davey, Hamilton (Folder 4)
  - DePierri, Kate P. (Folder 5)
  - Djilas, Milovan (Folder 6-7)
  - Groff, Jane (Folder 8)
  - Jackson, Henry M. (Folder 9)
  - Komunisticka Partija Jugoslavije, printed matter, 1948 (Folder 10-11)
  - Komunisticka Partija Jugoslavije, printed matter, 1948 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Ljotic, Vladimir (Folder 2)
  - Markovic, Mirko (Folder 3)
  - Mihailovich, Draza (Folder 4-5)
  - Mihajlov, Mihajlo (Folder 6)
  - Pasic, Nikola (Folder 7-11)
  - Pasic, Nikola (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
  - Prisoners of war, Yugoslavian, in Germany, 1944 (Folder 6)
  - Radic, Stjepa (Folder 7)
  - Salonika Trial, 1917 (Folder 8)
  - Serbia
    - Diplomatic history, 1893 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Foreign relations - Russia, Djordjevic, Vladan, "My Defense Before the Court," Belgrade, 1906 (Folder 2)
    - History
      - Pre-20th century (Folder 3-5)
      - 20th century Politics and government (Folder 6)
      - 1859-1875 (Folder 7)
      - 1879-1912 (Folder 8)
    - Printed matter
      - Garashanin, M.
        - Dva Namesnistva, Belgrade, 1893 (Folder 9)
        - Jedno Namesnikovaje, Belgrade, 1894 (Folder 10)
        - Zarad Istine i Pravde, Belgrade, 1890 (Folder 11)
      - Karich, V., Srbija i Balkanski Savez, Belgrade, 1890 (Folder 12)
      - Maksimovic, Milan M., Srbija za Vreme Namesnistva, Belgrade, 1872 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Marsanijanin, Tukhoslva, Engleska i Istocno Pitan'e, Belgrade, 1910 (Folder 2)
      - Milovanovic, M. B., O Parlamentarnoj Vladi, Belgrade, 1888 (Folder 3)
      - Nikasinovic, Bozhidar, Austro-Ugarska Politika Na Balkanu i Serbija, Belgrade, 1904 (Folder 4)
      - Radosavljevic, Steva Bdin, Pogonstvo Kral'itse Natalije, Belgrade, 1891 (Folder 5)
    - Social conditions, 1932 (Folder 6)
    - Stephan Dusan, Tsar (Folder 7)
  - Serbian National Committee (Chicago), Serbian Democratic Forum, No. 3, June 1973 (Folder 8)
  - Serbian Orthodox Church in the U.S., 1948 (Folder 9)
  - Simic, Djordje (Folder 10)
  - Tennessee delegate race, 1976 (Folder 11)
  - Tito, Josip Broz (Folder 12)
  - U.S. presidential campaign, 1976 (Folder 13)
  - University of Nashville, 1976-77 (Folder 14)
  - Vanderbilt University
    - General (Folder 15-16)
    - Courses, 1977-78 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Departmental information, 1977 (Folder 2)
    - Recruitment for senior position, 1977-78 (Folder 3)
  - Yugoslavia
    - Army, Austro-Hungarian officers, 1920 (Folder 4)
    - Chetniks (Folder 5)
    - Foreign relations - France, 1916 (Folder 6)
    - History
      - 20th century (Folder 7)
      - 1914-19 (Folder 8)
      - 1918-1945
        - General (Folder 9)
        - Markovic, Lazar
          - "From Serbia to Yugoslavia, 1903-1918," n.d. (Folder 10-11)
          - "From Serbia to Yugoslavia, 1903-1918," n.d. (Box 29, Folder 1)
          - "Zapisi o Dogadjajima u 1939 i 1940 Godinu," n.d. (Folder 2-6)
          - "Zapisi o Dogadjajima u 1939 i 1940 Godinu," n.d. (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - 1941-48 (Folder 2)
      - 1950 (Folder 3)
      - 1970-71 (Folder 4)
      - 1972-75 (Folder 5)
      - 1976-1980 (Folder 6-7)
      - 1980-82 (Folder 8)
    - Lovcen Monastery, 1969-1970 (Folder 9)
    - Maps (Folder 10)
    - Marxism
      - General (Folder 11)
      - Markovic, Sima, Natsionalno Pitaje u Svetlosti Marksizma, Belgrade, 1923 (Folder 12)
    - Nationalism (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Nationalities
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Jovanovic, Dragoljub, "Balkanci i Podunavci," 1958 (Folder 3)
    - Partisans, military strategy and tactics, 1939-1945 (Folder 4)
    - Philosophy professors, 1966-1975 (Folder 5)
    - Printed matter, Sisic, Ferdo, Predratna Politika Italije i Postanak Londonskog Pakta (1870-1915), Split, 1933 (Folder 6)
    - Selected newspaper issues, 1945-48 (Folder 7)
    - Social conditions
      - 1940-46 (Folder 8)
      - 1949-1950 (Folder 9)
    - Student demonstrations
      - 1968 (Folder 10)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Trade unions, 1934-37 (Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 3)
  - Yugoslavs in foreign countries, Iskra (Munich), 1953-54 (Folder 4)
  - Yugoslavs in the U.S., Croatian Home Defenders
    - General, 1936-1943 (Folder 5-7)
    - General, 1936-1943 (Box 33, Folder 1-3)
    - Doshen, Ante, excerpts from diary, 1937-1940 (Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
- Phonotape.
  - One phonotape of Sliv's account of his escape from a German prison of war camp during World War II. (Box Tape cabinet)
- Photographs.
  - 7 prints depicting A. Dragnich, Dragoljub Jovanovic, and others (Folder A)
  - 2 prints depicting the mausoleum of Josip Broz Tito (Folder B)
- Incremental Materials (Box 34-80)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu